Md Rayhanur Rahman

☑ mrahman87@ua.edu

• https://rayhanur-rahman.github.io

(D) 0000-0003-4980-7350

Google Scholar

№ DBLP

Summary

My research interests are software engineering and cybersecurity, focusing on mining actionable intelligence from open-source knowledge bases for software and security practitioners to design proactive defenses. I rely on a wide range of techniques, such as, natural language processing, machine learning, static analysis, and grounded theory-based approaches.

Education

2009 - 2012

2018 – 2024 Ph.D. in Computer Science, North Carolina State University

Thesis title: Towards mining proactive intelligence from OSCTI reports

Advisor: Dr. Laurie Williams Graduation: Fall 2024

2013 – 2014 M.Sc. in Software Engineering, University of Dhaka

Thesis title: Towards peer to peer resource provisioning in cloud

Advisor: Dr. Kazi Muheymin-Us-Sakib

B.IT. in Software Engineering, University of Dhaka

Work Experience

2024 – · · · Assistant Professor at the University of Alabama at Tuscaloosa

I will be joining the university as a tenure track assistant professor from August 2024 with a primary research focus on software engineering, cybersecurity, and machine learning.

2020 – 2020 Research Intern at Microsoft Corporation

I have worked with 1ES team to analyze and investigate how the security tools can be improved through empirical methods.

I served as a research assistant as part of NSA Science of Security Lablet. I investigate the open-source technical reports of past cyberattack incidents to mine malicious behavior patterns. I leverage the patterns to provide proactive and actionable insights for security practitioners. I also served as a teaching assistant for four semesters in software engineering, software security, and DevOps-related courses.

2021 – 2021 Summer Teaching Instructor at North Carolina State University

I have worked as a summer teaching instructor for C and Software Tools courses designed for undergraduate students.

2014 – 2018 Lecturer at University of Dhaka

I taught undergraduate courses such as Discrete Mathematics, Data Structure, Combinatorial Optimization, Object Oriented Concepts, and Operating Systems. I also taught Formal Methods and Models of Software Engineering to graduate students. Apart from teaching, I oversaw undergraduate students' academic affairs and designed course curricula for external institutions.

2015 – 2017 **Guest Lecturer** at Daffodil International University, Dhaka

I taught undergraduate courses: Software Engineering and Object-oriented Concepts.

2015 – 2016 **Quest Lecturer** at East West University, Dhaka

I taught undergraduate courses: Introduction to Computing.

2013 – 2014 **Junior Software Engineer** at Kaz Software

I worked on a proprietary Google Chrome extension named LinkableNews and a web application named LinkableService, which provided web ontology and identity services.

Selected Research Publications

Journal Articles (Published)

S. Elder, **Md Rayhanur Rahman**, G. finger, K. Kapoor, and L. Williams, "A survey on software vulnerability exploitability assessment," *ACM Computing Survey*, 2024.

- Md Rayhanur Rahman, R. Mahdavi-Hezaveh, and L. Williams, "What are the attackers doing now? automating cyberthreat intelligence extraction from text on pace with the changing threat landscape: A survey," ACM Computing Surveys, vol. 55, no. 12, pp. 1–36, 2023.
- Md Rayhanur Rahman, N. Imtiaz, M.-A. Storey, and L. Williams, "Why secret detection tools are not enough: It's not just about false positives-an industrial case study," *Empirical Software Engineering*, vol. 27, no. 3, p. 59, 2022.
- A. Rahman, **Md Rayhanur Rahman**, C. Parnin, and L. Williams, "Security smells in ansible and chef scripts: A replication study," *ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology (TOSEM)*, vol. 30, no. 1, pp. 1–31, 2021.
- M. M. Rahman, R. R. Riyadh, S. M. Khaled, A. Satter, and **Md Rayhanur Rahman**, "Mmruc3: A recommendation approach of move method refactoring using coupling, cohesion, and contextual similarity to enhance software design," *Software: Practice and Experience*, vol. 48, no. 9, pp. 1560–1587, 2018.
- **Md Rayhanur Rahman** and K. Sakib, "A scalable resource provisioning scheme for the cloud using peer to peer resource discovery and multi-attribute utility theory," *International Journal of Cloud Computing*, vol. 6, no. 3, pp. 211–237, 2017.
- M. M. Rahman, **Md Rayhanur Rahman**, and B. M. Hossain, "Recommendation of move method refactoring to optimize modularization using conceptual similarity," *International Journal of Information Technology and Computer Science*, 2017.
- M. M. Rahman, S. Rahman, **Md Rayhanur Rahman**, B. M. Hossain, and M. Shoyaib, "Dtcth: A discriminative local pattern descriptor for image classification," *EURASIP Journal on Image and Video Processing*, vol. 2017, pp. 1–24, 2017.
- A. Imran, A. U. Gias, **Md Rayhanur Rahman**, and K. Sakib, "Provintsec: A provenance cognition blueprint ensuring integrity and security for real life open source cloud," *International Journal of Information Privacy, Security and Integrity*, vol. 1, no. 4, pp. 360–380, 2013.

Conference Proceedings (Published)

- Md Rayhanur Rahman, W. Enck, and L. Williams, "Do configuration management tools make systems more secure? an empirical research plan," in *Proceedings of the 7th Symposium on Hot Topics in the Science of Security*, 2020, pp. 1–2.
- Md Rayhanur Rahman, R. Mahdavi-Hezaveh, and L. Williams, "A literature review on mining cyberthreat intelligence from unstructured texts," in 2020 International Conference on Data Mining Workshops (ICDMW), IEEE, 2020, pp. 516–525.
- Md Rayhanur Rahman, A. Rahman, and L. Williams, "Share, but be aware: Security smells in python gists," in 2019 IEEE International conference on software maintenance and evolution (ICSME), IEEE, 2019, pp. 536–540.
- A. S. Ami, M. M. Hasan, **Md Rayhanur Rahman**, and K. Sakib, "Mobicomonkey: Context testing of android apps," in *Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on Mobile Software Engineering and Systems*, 2018, pp. 76–79.

Conference Proceedings (Accepted)

M. R. Rahman, B. Wroblewski, M. Tamanna, I. Rahman, A. Anufryienak, and L. Williams, "Towards a taxonomy of challenges in security control implementation," in 2024 Annual Computer Security Application Conference, IEEE, 2024.

In Review

- **Md Rayhanur Rahman**, B. Wroblewski, M. Tamanna, I. Rahman, and L. Williams, "Towards a taxonomy of challenges in security control implementations," in *Annual Computer Application Security Conference*, 2024.
- Md Rayhanur Rahman, R. Mahdavi-Hezaveh, S. Basak, and L. Williams, "Attackers reveal their arsenal: An investigation of adversarial techniques in cti reports," ACM Transactions on Privacy and Security, 2023.
- Md Rayhanur Rahman, B. Wroblewski, Q. Matthews, B. Morgan, T. Menzies, and L. Williams, "Mining temporal attack patterns from cyberthreat intelligence reports," *IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering*, 2023.

Preprints

Md Rayhanur Rahman and L. Williams, "An investigation of security controls and mitre att\&ck techniques," arXiv preprint arXiv:2211.06500, 2022.

- Md Rayhanur Rahman and L. Williams, "From threat reports to continuous threat intelligence: A comparison of attack technique extraction methods from textual artifacts," arXiv preprint arXiv:2210.02601, 2022.
- Md Rayhanur Rahman and L. Williams, "Investigating co-occurrences of mitre att\&ck techniques," arXiv preprint arXiv:2211.06495, 2022.

Skills

Research methods	Mixed methods, meta-analysis, grounded theory approach, survey, empirical anal-
	vsis

Machine learning Classical learning, deep learning, graph learning, multi-modal learning, association rule mining, social network analysis

Natural language processing Transformers, large language models, language representation learning, fine-tuning, semantic analysis, text classification, entity and relation extraction, knowledge graph extraction

Cybersecurity Threat intelligence, security control, threat modelling, MITRE ATT&CK, NVD, CWE, NIST SP800-53, vulnerability analysis

Tools PyTorch, Deep graph library, Scikit-learn, Networkx, Spacy, OpenAI, Transformers, CodeQL, ZAP, Fortify

Languages Python, C#, Javascript, Prolog, Java, C

Research Tools

ChronoCTI Extracting temporal patterns of malicious malware behavior from open source textual descriptions of past cyberattacks

PyGistSecuritySmell A static analyzer for finding security weaknesses in Python

SLIC-Ansible A static analyzer for finding security weaknesses in Ansible scripts

Scalable-VFDT An online tree based learner for software defect predictions for large-scale codebases

Miscellaneous

Scholarly Contribution

Guest Talk Large Language Models and Secure Coding, NC State University

Reviewer for Heliyon

2023 **Reviewer** for Computers & Security

Guest Talk Inviting Security and Privacy into DevOps, NC State University

2021 **Sub-reviewer** for International Conference of Software Engineering

Sub-reviewer for International Conference of Software Engineering

2020 **Sub-reviewer** for Mining Software Repositories

Sub-reviewer for Empirical Software Engineering Methods, and Measurements

Teaching

2014-2018 Undergraduate courses: Discrete Mathematics, Object-oriented Concepts, Combinatorial Optimization, Operating System and System Programming, Distributed Systems, Computer Data and Network Security, Introduction to Computing

Graduate courses: Formal Methods and Models in Software Engineering, Distributed Software Engineering

2021 Undergraduate courses: C and Software Tools

2018-2024 **Teaching Assistant:** Software Engineering, DevOps, Software Security

Miscellaneous (continued)

Mentoring

2024 Undergraduate students: Brandon Wroblewski, Andrew Anufryienak

2023 Undergraduate students: Brantley Morgan, Brandon Wroblewski, Quinn Matthews

2022 Undergraduate students: Jonathan Buck

2021 Graduate students: Aishwarya Seth

2017 Graduate Students: Deepak Chandra Das

2016 Graduate Students: Masudur Rahman

2015 **Graduate Students**: Md Shafiuzzaman

Awards and Achievements

2024 Mentored Teaching Fellowship - Software Security, College of Engineering, NC State University

2020 Travel Grant, Science of Security, National Security Agency

Travel Grant, College of Engineering, NC State University, United States

2017 Research Grant, United Grants Commission, Bangladesh

2016 Research Grant, United Grants Commission, Bangladesh

Innovation Fund, Ministry of Information, Communication and Technology, Government of

Bangladesh

National Science and Technology Fellowship, Ministry of Science and Technology, Government

of Bangladesh

Finalist, Microsoft Imagine Cup, Bangladesh

2011 Champion, GetRoot Cybersecurity Challenge, organized by OWASP, Bangladesh

References

1. Dr. Laurie Williams

Distinguished University Professor, Computer Science, NC State University

Email: lawilli3@ncsu.edu

Cell: 919-513-4151

2. Dr. Munindar P. Singh

SAS Institute Distinguished Professor of Computer Science, Computer Science, NC State University

Email: mpsingh@ncsu.edu

Cell: 919-515-5677

3. Dr. Timothy Menzies

Professor, Computer Science, NC State University

Email: tjmenzie@ncsu.edu

Cell: 304-376-2859

4. Dr. Akond Rahman

Assistant Professor, Computer Science and Software Engineering, Auburn University

Email: akond@auburn.edu

Cell: 334-844-6352

5. Dr. John-Paul Ore

Assistant Professor, Computer Science, NC State University

Email: jwore@ncsu.edu

Cell: 919-515-5164